Okay, good afternoon, good morning or good night,
好的，下午好，早上好或晚上好，
let's get started,
我们开始吧,
today I want to talk about Bitcoin.
今天我想谈谈比特币。
The reason I want to talk about it is,
我想谈这件事的原因是，
it solves a hard problem,
它解决了一个困难的问题，
namely achieving consensus with byzantine participants.
也就是与拜占庭参与者达成共识。
I think it solved,
我想它解决了，
so byzantine I mean participants is that,
所以拜占庭参与者是，
it might be a malicious or adversarial,
它可能是恶意的或敌意的，
and it solves this problem in the context of a completely open systems,
它在一个完全开放的系统中解决了这个问题，
you know people can join and leave the system as will,
人们可以随意加入和离开这个系统，
and some of them may be malicious,
其中一些可能是恶意的，
and yet you know achieve consensus on the order in which transaction happen.
并在事务发生的顺序上达成共识。
So does it actually a very challenging context,
这是一个非常具有挑战性的情况，
is actually really doing in the money involved.
是涉及到钱的。
The design you know looks a little bit like has aspects of SUNDR,
这个设计有点像 SUNDR 的一些方面，
so in the sence,
在这个意义上，
there's a signed log of operations,
有一个有签名的操作日志，
in this case transactions.
在这个事务的例子中。
We know like in SUNDR, that actually you can handle forks,
我们知道在 SUNDR 中，可以处理 fork ，
so most of the, many aspects that are interesting to talk about with respect to Bitcoin,
所以，关于比特币的大部分，很多有趣的方面，
but mostly I'm going to focus on
我主要将重点放在
sort of sort of the distributed systems aspect of this particular paper.
这篇论文的分布式系统方面。
This paper is a bit unusual or quite unusual,
这篇论文有点不同寻常，或者说相当不同寻常，
first of all, it's not a paper out of the scientific literature,
首先，这不是一篇来自科学文献的论文，
that I've been reading so far,
目前为止我所读过的，
it comes out of a different part of the world,
它来自世界上不同的地方，
it is pseudo-anonymous,
它是匿名的，
and it has you know particularly [] you know with a financial institutions,
而且它有特别的[]，对于一家金融机构，
and you know you can have all kinds of opinions
你可以有各种各样的意见，
about Bitcoin in general and cryptocurrency in general,
关于通常的比特币和加密货币，
but from the perspective of distributed systems,
但从分布式系统的角度来看，
this is a [] successful system,
这是一个[]成功的系统，
this is a really truly an open system,
这是一个真正开放的系统，
that can tolerate the byzantine participants and achieving consensus.
可以容忍拜占庭参与者，并达成共识。
And so really, you know the focus of this lecture,
所以这节课的重点，
you're trying to understand
你在试图理解，
how actually achieves that particular aspect.
如何实现这一特定方面。
Any questions, just do before diving in?
有任何问题吗，在开始讨论之前？
Okay, so as I just mentioned,
好的，就像我刚才提到的，
you know the context is here financial transactions.
这里的背景是金融交易。
And so there's a free overriding concerns,
所以，这里有一个压倒一切的担忧，
you know when, when transactions are involved,
当涉及到交易时，
where money transactions are involved,
在涉及金钱交易时，
first of all, of course there's the concern outright forgery,
首先，当然担心完全的伪造，
where basically you know people cook up transactions out of thin air,
人们凭空捏造交易，
and enter them in the log,
并将它们输入到日志中，
and you know trying to mislead other participants,
试图误导其他参与者，
you know that actually they're spending their own money,
实际上他们是在花自己的钱，
while spending somebody else's money,
同时花别人的钱，
and you know this problem is reasonably straightforward for solved,
这个问题很容易解决，
in a very short similar style to SUNDR,
以一种非常短的类似于 SUNDR 的风格，
but basically signing operations make it hard to actually forge,
从根本上说，签名操作使伪造变得困难，
and in fact you know the general setting here, correct,
事实上，这里的大体情况，
it's the same as in SUNDR,
它和 SUNDR 是一样的，
well, you know the byzantine participants are very very powerful,
拜占庭参与者非常强大，
we're going to be assuming
我们将假设
that the crypto systems actually work and cannot be compromised.
密码系统是工作的，不会被攻破。
And so a lot of the core functionality or the basis
所以，许多核心功能或基础，
of which you know we might conclude,
我们可能会包括，
that actually things are secure, all going to come down
一切都很安全，一切是好的，
to the fact that the underlying cryptography is correct,
基于基础密码学是正确的这一事实，
so that's one challenge.
所以这是一个挑战。
The second challenge which is the one,
第二个挑战是，
that the paper spends mosts of time talking about is double spending,
论文花了很多时间讨论的是双重花费，
so you literally have you know some Bitcoins, that you accumulated,
所以你有一些比特币，你积累的，
and a byzantine practitioner tries to spend twice that same Bitcoin,
一个拜占庭参与者试图花费同一个比特币两次，
and of course we want to avoid that particular problem I do,
当然，我们想要避免那个特别的问题，
and the main ideas we'll see is
我们将看到的主要想法是
a public ledger or a public log of all the transactions,
所有交易的公共账本或公共日志，
you know so you can see if the transaction actually,
所以你可以看到交易是否，
without money was already spending early transaction,
没有钱已经在早期的交易花费，
and really trying to achieve consensus on what is actually in the log,
并试图在日志中的内容达成共识，
is the heart of the paper.
是这篇论文的核心。
Then, of course, in addition to these two,
当然除了这两个之外，
you know the obvious other problem,
另一个显而易见的问题，
which paper doesn't talk much about,
但论文没有太多地谈到，
and we're also not gonna talk much about
我们也不会谈论太多，
which is just theft,
也就是偷窃，
where somebody actually steal somebody else's private key,
有人偷了别人的私钥，
and therefore can spend money or Bitcoins
因此可以花钱或使用比特币，
using that particular private key,
使用这个特定私钥，
and it turns out to be in practice a serious problem,
这是一个严重的问题，
people store their wallets with their signing keys on computers,
人们将他们的钱包和他们的签名密钥存储在计算机上，
and computers can be broken into,
电脑可以被破解，
and and therefore people can break it over, steals somebody else's money.
因此，人们可以打破它，偷窃别人的钱。
And I think this is a serious problem in practice,
我认为这在实践中是一个严重的问题，
I'm not going to be spending much time talking about it,
我不会花太多时间谈论这件事，
again I want to focus on the distributed system's aspects.
再一次，我想集中讨论分布式系统方面。
Any questions about the challenges?
对这些挑战，有什么问题吗？
Okay, let's look at the transaction,
好的，我们来看看交易，
you know what's actually in it.
它里面是什么。
So this is basically what is in the ledger,
所以这是什么在账本中，
I'm going simplify this greatly,
我将大大简化这一过程，
because some of the details actually don't really matter to the discussion,
因为一些细节对讨论不重要，
that we're going to have,
我们将要进行的（讨论），
and the first [order] you can think about is,
你能想到的第一个[顺序]是，
every transaction is a record,
每一笔交易都是一个记录，
and the record has a public key,
并且记录具有公钥，
for the user, for which you know the the money is intended,
对于持有钱的用户，
so this is the destination,
所以这就是目的，
a hash of the previous transaction,
之前交易的哈希，
you know for this particular Bitcoin,
对于这种特殊的比特币来说，
and a signature, and we have the private key,
以及签名，我们有私钥，
U2 you know were basically the previous owner of that particular Bitcoin,
U2 是这个比特币的前所有者，
and in that sort of you can think about this as the source,
在这种情况下，你可以认为这是来源，
so basically U2 is making
所以 U2 操作，
you know granting you know Bitcoin, transferring Bitcoins from U2 to U1,
同意将比特币从 U2 转移到 U1 ，
so that U1 that can spend them.
这样 U1 可以花掉它们。
Of course, there's all kind of other stuff in it,
当然，里面还有很多其他的东西，
like there's an amount in it,
比如有一个金额，
it's a fractional amount,
一个零钱金额，
there are many destinations and many sources possible,
可能有许多目的地和许多来源，
there are many ins and outs,
有很多进出，
we are basically will ignore it,
我们都会忽略它，
and just focus on a sort of simplified description,
只专注于一种简化的描述，
turns out that transactions are encoded also
事实证明，交易也是编码的，
not sort of like sort of [passive] records,
而不是某种被动记录，
but basically a little scripting language,
但是一种小的脚本语言，
and also going to ignore all those aspects.
也会忽略所有这些方面。
I'm going to start to focus on this thing,
我将开始专注于这件事，
and you know talk a little bit and show a little example,
然后讨论，展示一个小例子，
so we get a little bit of handle
所以我们得到一点了解，
and actually what we're looking at in terms of the challenge.
我们所看到的就是这一挑战。
So we're going to sort of look at an example ledger
所以，我们将查看一个示例账本，
and sort of trying to understand
试图理解，
actually you know what it means to be a Bitcoin or what a coin is,
比特币意味着什么或者币是什么，
it's not like sort of a single thing,
这不是一件单一的事情，
actually it really comes down to is
这可以归结为
actually sort of a sha1 of the last transaction,
上一笔交易的 sha1 ，
that's sort of what a coin is.
这就是硬币的本质。
So let's say you know y owns a coin and received from x,
所以，假设 y 有一枚币，从 x 那里收到，
and so that means that there's somewhere in the ledger,
所以这意味着在账本的某个地方，
that sort of transactions,
这个交易，
that transfer the money or the coin or parts of the coin to y,
转移钱或币或币的一部分给 y ，
and so let's see,
让我们看看，
like somewhere, maybe there was an entry that ledger somewhere,
在某个地方，可能有一个条目在账本中，
in some period time, where x actually received some Bitcoins,
在一段时间内， x 收到了一些比特币，
and, and now you know sort of grants the, has given it to y.
现在已经把它给了 y 。
So there's another transaction in the ledger,
所以在账本上还有另一笔交易，
that basically records that fact,
记录了这样一个事实，
and so that might have a pub key of y,
所以它可能有 y 的公钥，
destination the hash of the transaction 6,
目的地交易 6 的哈希值，
and so that uniquely identifies shorthand handle
所以这唯一标记了标志，
for uniquely identifying transaction 6,
唯一标识交易 6 ，
and so we have the ledger or record, we think is transaction 6,
所以我们有交易 6 的账本或记录，
now we can re-compute the hash of that transaction
现在我们可以重新计算这个交易的哈希值，
compared to the one that storage transaction 7,
与存储交易 7 相比，
and where truly determined that basically transaction 6,
确定了事务 6 ，
what's the source you know for this transaction 7,
这笔交易的来源是什么，
or it's based the previous transaction, was transaction 6, for this particular coin,
或者它是基于之前交易 6 ，对于这个币，
it is signed by you know x.
它是由 x 签名的。
Now, so this is sort of situation,
现在，这是一种情况，
where y obtained basically you know some Bitcoins you know from x,
y 从 x 获取一些比特币，
you know y wants to spend,
y 想要花掉，
for example, maybe y want to buy a latte from z,
例如，也许 y 想从 z 买一杯拿铁，
and so it's transfer some money to z,
所以它向 z 的转一笔钱，
so maybe we'll see another transaction in the ledger,
所以也许我们会在账本上看到另一笔交易，
which is going to be a form,
这将是一种形式，
this is one that actually y is going to add,
这是 y 要加上，
pub(z), hash of the previous coin,
pub(z) ，上一个币的哈希值，
the last transaction for that coin, so that's,
那枚币的最后一笔交易，是 T7 ，
and you know sign by y.
并由 y 签名。
Basically you know z wants to do,
z 想做的，
before you know z actually hands over the latte to y,
在 z 把拿铁给了 y 之前，
z need to do some verification
z 需要做一些验证
to make sure that this actually is a legit you know transaction,
以确保这是合法的交易，
so you know look up you know transaction 7,
所以查看交易 7 ，
and you know compute you know the hash of double check,
计算哈希值，进行检查，
the hash actually corresponds to the one
哈希值对应于
that actually listed in transaction, in transaction 8,
交易 8 中列出的哈希值，
if you know the hash checks out,
如果哈希值已通过，
so there's transaction 7 is indeed,
所以这是交易 7 ，
you know we believe that the one that actually transaction 8 refers to,
我们相信交易 8 所指的，
you know z looks up the public key in transaction 7 for y,
z 在交易 7 中查找 y 的公钥，
which usually is the public key y,
通常是公钥 y ，
then you know verifies that use that public key
然后验证使用这个公钥
to verify the signature of this transaction,
来验证这个交易的签名，
and the signature of course covers the whole transaction,
签名当然涵盖了整个交易，
and if the signature checks out,
如果签名通过了，
you know then you know z can be confident
然后 z 可以自信地，
you know that actually the ledger contains a transaction,
账本包含一个交易，
that basically transfers you know some amount of money from y to z,
将一些钱从 y 转移到 z ，
so at this point, you know the verification you know z verifies,
所以在这一点上， z 验证了，
and you know if it's okay, you know whatever ship latte,
如果它是好的，给出拿铁，
and if not, you know reject,
如果不是，就拒绝，
and again like before in you know the SUNDR,
又一次，就像在 SUNDR 中，
and all these sort of schemes you know we're lying here in the fact,
所有这些方案都在这里，
that basically y you know was careful with its private key,
y 很小心地使用它的私钥，
so you know we have to assume,
所以我们必须假设，
that y didn't disclose in any way it's private key,
y 没有以任何方式透露它的私钥，
because if anybody has you know this private key,
因为如果有人知道这个私钥，
then there's anybody could come up to signature,
那么任何人都可以签名，
and you know he was able to spend basically y's money,
他可以花掉 y 的钱，
although maybe from the perspective receiver, doesn't really care.
虽然可能从接受者的角度来看，并不是真的在乎。
Okay, so, so that's sort of basic plan,
好的，所以，这是一个基本的计划，
in terms of having a record,
就有记录而言，
I mean, you know this is pretty good,
我是说，这很好，
I mean, there's a record of the transaction that happened,
我是说，有交易的记录，
when z receives a transaction,
当 z 接收到交易，
that could check whether this is a valid transaction,
可以检查这是否是有效的交易，
and that you know allows to decide
这允许决定，
where to actually accept the money and deliver the goods.
接受资金和交付货物。
So, one key challenge you know in,that,
所以，其中一个关键挑战，
you know sort of left,
所说的，
you know we're seeing that outright forgery is difficult,
我们看到完全伪造是很困难的，
but you know we need to think a little bit about the double spending,
但我们需要考虑一下双重花费，
and so the double spending problem is as follows.
所以，双重花费问题如下所示。
Let's say instead of creating two record, one record
假设不是创建一个记录，
in this particular example in the transaction the 8,
在这个交易 8 的例子中，
z actually you know creates, [] y creates two records,
z 创建了， y 创建了两个记录，
one record is basically giving the one that you saw you know are T8,
一个记录是你看到的那个 T8 ，
y to z, with hash T7.
y 到 z ，以及 T7 的哈希值。
And let's see,
让我们来看看，
let's assume that actually y also tries to double spend its money,
让我们假设 y 试图双重花费它的钱，
so it creates a second transaction T8',
所以它创建了第二个交易 T8' ，
where you know the records is basically the same,
记录基本上是一样的，
except the money goes to Q,
除了钱流向了 Q ，
and it hash of T7,
它有 T7 的哈希，
and of course you know sign by y,
当然也有 y 的签名，
you know signed by y.
由 y 签名。
Now, you know let's say you know both q and z are latte stores,
现在，假设 q 和 z 都是拿铁咖啡店，
if you know z accepts T8,
如果 z 接受了 T8 ，
as it would,
它会这么做，
because you know everything will check out
因为一切检查都通过了，
as we saw in the previous slide,
正如我们在上一张幻灯片中所看到的，
then z would actually ship a latte to y,
然后 z 会把一杯拿铁给 y ，
when q not knowing anything,
q 不知道任何事情，
maybe about this other T8 transaction,
可能关于另一笔 T8 交易，
since this T8 transaction,
因为这个 T8 交易，
you know check it out,
检查这个，
it's indeed the case,
确实是这样，
that you know the money in T7 was transferred to y,
T7 中的钱被转移到了 y ，
the thing is you know checked you know with signature for y,
检查了 y 的签名，
you know if valid and will say okay great,
如果有效，会说好的，很好，
you know, oh, thank you for the money,
哦，谢谢你的钱，
I'll ship you also a latte,
我也会给你一杯拿铁，
and now we're in this bad position,
现在我们的处境很糟糕，
where y by double spending or succeeded in double spending and got two lattes,
因为 y 成功双重花费并得到两杯拿铁，
you know there's the problem,
这是那个问题，
that basically the paper really focused on trying to solve.
论文致力于解决的问题。
The basic approach is,
基本的方法是，
you know sort of similar to what somewhere was doing,
有点类似于做过的事情，
let's keep a complete log of all transactions,
我们记录所有的交易日志，
since the beginning of time,
从它们一开始，
and in the log contains all the transactions including the order, right,
在日志中包含所有交易，包括顺序，
and so you know let's see you know,
所以，让我们看看，
so we sort of put the transactions in,
所以我们把交易放进去，
you know whatever here we had T6, here we had T7,
我们这里有 T6 ，这里有 T7 ，
so if there's a public record,
所以如果有公共记录，
that is ordered to all the transactions,
它对所有交易进行排序，
you know T8 or T8' goes first,
T8 或 T8' 先开始，
let's say T8 goes first,
假设 T8 先开始，
and then the T8' goes in the log,
然后 T8' 进入日志中，
and you know this would happen,
这会发生，
then you have no problem at all, right,
那么你一点问题都没有，
because this was the transaction from y to z,
因为这是从 y 到 z 的交易，
this was the transaction from y to Q,
这是从 y 到 q 的交易，
and you know basically when q validates,
当 Q 确认的时候，
you know when z validates transaction,
当 z 确认交易时，
everything looks perfect as exactly as before,
一切看起来都和以前一样完美，
when Q validates the transaction,
当 Q 确认交易时，
in addition to the checks, that we just looked at,
除了检查，我们查看，
it actually looks in the log,
它在日志中查找，
Q looks in the log,
Q 在日志中查找，
like to see T7 basically is already spent,
看到 T7 已经花掉了，
and of course you step back the log, you know runs into Ty T8,
当然，你后退日志，遇到 T8 ，
and you know sees actually the money has been spent,
看到钱已经花掉了，
so therefore it will reject you know T8'.
所以，它将拒绝 T8' 。
Alright?
好吗？
So, so that's the basic plan,
所以，这就是基本计划，
and so basically you know produces one problem,
所以产生了一个问题，
which is like how do we actually ensure that,
比如我们如何确保，
all participants in the systems actually agree on this log,
系统中的所有参与者都同意这个日志，
and you know all the transactions are in the same slot everywhere,
所有的交易都在同一个位置，
and contain the same content, the same hashes, the same signatures,
包含相同的内容、相同的散列、相同的签名，
so that we can actually verify the transactions,
所以，我们可以验证交易，
you know using scheme are laid out in this slide.
使用这个幻灯片中列出的方案。
And so this is where sort of consensus problem comes in,
这就是共识问题的作用，
and sometimes people refer to this solution here
有时，人们将这一解决方案
as the Nakamoto consensus protocol.
称为中本聪共识协议。
Now before diving into that protocol,
现在，在深入研究协议之前，
I want to sketch out you know possible solutions,
我想勾勒出可能的解决方案，
that are not going to work,
它们是行不通的，
just to get a better sense,
只是为了得到更好的感觉，
but like what the challenges are,
比如挑战是什么，
this sort of Nakamoto consensus actually solves.
这种中本聪共识所解决的。
So you know design 1,
所以设计 1 ，
there's not really design,
这并不是真正的设计，
it's more sort of an idea to think about and then reject,
它更像是一种考虑的方法，然后拒绝，
design 1 may be the easiest design is,
设计 1 可能是最简单的设计，
let's assume we have the server S,
假设我们有服务器 S ，
and the server actually just trusted,
而且服务器是受信任的，
and then we have clients you know that,
然后我们有客户端，
you know there some transactions, whatever T6,
有一些交易，不管是 T6 ，
1 2, whatever x y z,
1 2 ， x y z ，
and they just submit you know these transactions to the, to the trusted server,
它们只是把这些交易提交给可信服务器，
you know after we all the clients trust the server,
所有的客户端都信任这个服务器，
and the server can just produce a log, right,
服务器可以生成一个日志，
with all the transactions in it,
有所有的交易，
and you know order them appropriately etc, etc.
对它们进行排序，等等。
So if we assume there's a trusted server,
所以，如果我们假设有一个受信任的服务器，
and this problem is actually reasonably straightforward to solve,
这个问题很容易解决，
and you know that's setting we're in,
我们所处的环境，
that we're in great [shape],
我们处于很好的状态，
you know maybe replicate the server using you know some Raft type protocol,
可能使用某种 Raft 类型的协议复制服务器，
and you know we'll have a fault tolerance server,
我们会有一个容错服务器，
and you know really the only downside to this particular process is,
这个特殊过程的唯一缺点是，
if the clients could not agree on a single trusted server,
如果客户端不能同意单个可信服务器，
and so an example in the case of Bitcoin,
以比特币为例，
when you want to do transactions,
当你想做交易的时候，
you know maybe the,
也许，
you know the rest of the world going to trust the US government
世界其他国家会信任美国政府，
to actually implement the server correctly and produce a log,
正确地实现服务器并生成日志，
and in that case, you know we have multiple different clients,
在这种情况下，我们有多个不同的客户端，
because you cannot agree on a trusted server,
因为你无法同意一个受信任的服务器，
then this solution, this serve doesn't work.
然后这个解决方案，这个服务就不管用了。
So that's one solution,
所以这是一种解决方案，
it's the easy one,
这是简单的一个，
but in the case of decentralized design,
但在去中心化设计的情况下，
where there's no trust any central component,
没有信任的任何核心组件，
this is not a workable solution.
这不是一个可行的解决方案。
So, so now we consider using sort of the more SUNDR like approach,
所以，现在我们考虑使用像 SUNDR 的方法，
to modify scheme slightly,
对方案稍加修改，
and say like okay good,
然后说，好的，好的，
we know actually how to deal with untrusted servers,
我们知道如何处理不可信的服务器，
in fact we read a paper about it last week.
事实上，我们上周读了关于它的论文。
And so let's assume that these servers actually untrusted,
所以，让我们假设这些服务器是不受信任的，
and you know basically you play the SUNDR game,
你玩的是 SUNDR 的游戏，
clients produce the logs, read the logs from the server,
客户端生成日志，从服务器读取日志，
and append records to the, append the records to the log,
将记录追加到日志中，
submit it back to the server,
将其提交回服务器，
so the server is basically do almost nothing else,
所以，服务器基本上不做其他任何事情，
that's relaying logs between different clients,
它在不同的客户端之间转发日志，
and we've seen last week,
我们上周已经看到，
that actually approach works really well,
这种方法确实效果很好，
it can be used,
它可以被使用，
but you know it has one shortcoming as we saw,
但是，正如我们所见，它有一个缺点，
namely the server can present two different views of the world
也就是说，服务器可以呈现两种不同的世界观，
by basically forking the log,
通过 fork 日志，
so maybe the log has some prefix,
所以也许日志有一些前缀，
you know T1 to T2 to T5 to 6 7,
T1 T2 到 T5 T6 T7 ，
but now it has T8 in this one,
但现在这里有 T8 ，
and has another log,
还有另一个日志，
which indeed has T7 ... and T8'.
包含 T7 ... 和 T8' 。
And so one fork you know we've got T8,
所以在一个 fork ，我们得到 T8 ，
on the other fork, we have T8',
在另一个 fork ，我们有 T8' ，
and now like we became re or settle in one particular fork,
现在我们选择一个 fork ，
and the server sort of persistently you know keeps the two worlds apart,
服务器将这两个世界分开，
like the y is, and z is in one area of the world,
比如 z 在一个世界，
Q is in another in the world,
Q 在另一个世界，
y always gets the first sort of log,
y 总是得到第一个日志，
and z always gets the second one log, the other way around,
z 总是得到第二个日志，正好相反，
then, you know,
然后，你知道，
then they will pretend there's okay, good,
然后它们会假装，好的，好的，
yeah, there's no money earlier spending T7 in this log,
是的，在这个日志中没有之前花费 T7 ，
so T8 in Q will actually accept,
所以 Q 中的 T8 会接受，
you know T8' in this world,
在这个世界的 T8' ，
and here z will accept you know T8,
这里 z 将接受 T8 ，
and so y succeeded in actually double spending.
所以， y 成功地实现了双重花费。
So, this design doesn't work,
所以，这个设计不能工作，
for the particular problem at hand,
对于这个问题，
we need some solution
我们需要一些解决方案，
and is where the consensus comes in,
这也是共识的地方。
that basically for the untrusted clients
让不受信任的客户端
to basically be able to settle on which you know fork they are on.
能够解决它们在哪个 fork 。
Okay, so, in, so let's think a little bit about that,
好的，所以，让我们稍微想一想，
so let's think about more much more decentralized design,
所以想一想更加去中心化的设计，
we're going to replace the server with a network of computers.
我们将用计算机网络取代服务器。
So, this is there,
所以，在那里，
and this goes sort of to get closer to the Bitcoin design,
这离比特币设计更近，
where there's indeed a network of peers,
那里有一个节点网络，
that's sort of all collaborate together
所有这些都在某种程度上合作，
to provide you know this single log,
以提供这个单一日志，
although even though some of the participants actually might be malicious,
尽管有些参与者可能是恶意的，
and try to do something different.
尝试做一些不同的事情。
And so basically the idea is that,
所以我们的想法是，
when a client actually you know create a transaction,
当客户端创建交易时，
you know then transaction is distributed across a network of peers,
然后交易在节点网络中分发，
in fact, the client 1 might be a peer himself,
事实上，客户端 1 自己可能是一个节点，
so the transaction is going to spread around,
所以，交易将传播到各处，
and you know everybody every node in the network actually maintains a log,
网络中的每个节点都维护着一个日志，
and appends you know the transaction to its log.
并将交易附加到它的日志中。
And the problem that we have left is,
我们剩下的问题是，
like you know how to agree on an order.
如何就顺序达成一致。
And you know we we actually have seen these kind of systems before,
我们以前见过这样的系统，
like in fact in Raft,
比如在 Raft 中，
you know we had multiple computers,
我们有多个计算机，
and they were able to agree on order, right,
它们能够就顺序达成一致，
and the basic trick, was used as a basic inside is,
基本的技巧，在其中使用的是，
you know basically compute some majority
计算某个大多数，
and have a majority of nodes agree
有大多数节点达成一致，
in slot you know 6 is gonna be transaction T8,
插槽 6 是事务 T8 ，
and in slot 7 is going to be T8'.
在插槽 7 中，将是 T8' 。
And the, and that works great, correct,
而且，这很有效，
if we know exactly how many nodes are in the system,
如果我们确切地知道系统中有多少个节点，
we know there's 5 nodes in the system,
我们知道系统中有 5 个节点，
the node and then the majority is 3,
然后大多数是 3 ，
and we receive response from 3 participants,
我们收到了 3 个参与者的回复，
you know we know okay, we can commit that particular slot.
我们知道，好的，我们可以提交那个位置。
And the problem really here is that,
这里真正的问题是，
this is a decentralized system, that's completely open,
这是一个去中心化的系统，这是完全开放的，
the system nodes might even may leave, may come in any particular point of time,
系统节点甚至可能在任何时间离开、到来，
and there is no list of all the participants in system,
在系统中没有所有参与者的列表，
so there's also no clear what actually what is a majority in the system like that,
所以，也不清楚在这样的系统中到底什么是多数，
because it's completely open,
因为它是完全开放的，
so it's like the notion of the majority is completely able to find.
所以大多数的概念能够找到。
So you know we need some sort of, like a sort of usual game,
所以我们需要一些像往常一样的游戏，
sort of doing voting on a majority
对大多数进行投票，
and then accept the result of the majority is not going to play out,
然后接受多数人的结果是不会奏效的，
and so this is the the game sort of Raft,
这是 Raft 的游戏，
you know even though it's a consensus protocol, not gonna really work out,
即使这是一个共识协议，也不会奏效，
because you know the setting we're dealing with is
因为我们在处理的环境是
a decentralized open distributed system,
一个去中心化的开放分布式系统，
as opposed to a closed system as in the setting of Raft.
而不是像 Raft 设置中的封闭系统。
Does this make sense so far?
到目前为止，能理解吗？
Let me pause for a second,
让我暂停一下，
before getting into the more technical part.
在进入更技术性的部分之前。
Alright?
好的？
Okay, so how does Bitcoin solve this problem?
好的，那么比特币是如何解决这个问题的？
And the key idea is something that is called the proof-of-work,
关键的想法是所谓的工作量证明，
basically the rule is that,
基本上规则是，
there's a mount of work a node needs to do
一个节点需要完成大量的工作，
to actually be able to extend the log,
才能扩展日志，
and the basic rule is that,
在基本规则中，你知道的工作机器证明中的赢家
the winner in you know proof-of-work,
工作量证明的胜利者，
machine is able to solve the puzzle,
机器能够解决那个难题，
first, it decides on the next log entry,
首先，它决定下一个日志条目，
and the basic idea,
基本的想法，
that this might you might actually get some intuition,
这可能会让你得到一些直觉，
why this action will work out,
为什么这个操作有效，
is because basically hard to impersonate the winner
因为很难冒充获胜者，
to actually solve the particular proof-of-work puzzle,
解决这个特殊的工作量证明难题，
that needs to be able to add to the log,
需要能够添加到日志中，
actually requires a real computer,
实际上需要一台计算机，
in a month getting roughly of compute time
在一个月的计算时间，
to actually solve the problem,
来解决这个问题，
and so if you can solve and demonstrate you solve the problem,
所以，如果你能解决，并证明你解决了问题，
you know for sure that somebody actually spent a month of work actually do it,
可以肯定的是，有人花了一个月的时间去做，
and this is sort of enough of to convince you know the rest of the system,
这在某种程度上足以让你相信系统的其余部分，
that you know there's a real resources were actually spent
需要花费真正的资源，
to append, to be able to append to the log entry,
以便能够追加到日志条目，
and and you can maybe think of others like the schemes,
也许你可以想到其他类似的方案，
like whatever you know unique IP addresses or things like that,
比如唯一的 IP 地址或类似的东西，
but all those kind of things can be actually easily falsified,
但所有这些东西都很容易被篡改，
and so it's sort of proof-of-work idea is sort of core core
所以工作量证明的想法是核心，
to demonstrate that, actually you know put a month effort into actually,
为了证明，花了一个月的时间，
to figure out what the next [], to compute,
计算出下一个[]，
to be able to be able to append a log entry to the log.
能够将日志条目追加到日志中。
One, you know just get that immediately out of the way,
一个，这个方法，
one of downside of this proof-of-work approach is that,
这种工作证明方法的一个缺点是，
it actually waste energy,
它在浪费能量，
and in fact you know Bitcoins become so successful,
事实上，比特币会如此成功，
that a lot of people are down there,
很多人都在下面，
are you know mining and doing this proof-of-work,
挖掘和做这项工作量证明，
that the energy bill or energy consumption
能量账单或者能量消耗，
of all the combined miners together is incredibly significant,
所有矿工统计在一起是难以置信的大，
it's huge,
它很大，
and so, play downside of this approach is the waste of energy.
所以，这种方法的负面影响是浪费能源。
In recent years, there have been other crypto currencies or other designs,
近年来，出现了其他加密货币或其他设计，
that are based on a different idea,
基于不同的想法，
instead of proof-of-work,
不是工作量证明，
they're actually based on something else called proof-of-stake,
而是基于称为权益证明的东西，
and this basically sort of game there is,
这是一种游戏，
you know let's say you own 3% of you know the currency,
假设你拥有 3% 的货币，
then you get,
然后你可以，
because you own 3%,
因为你拥有 3% ，
you can actually decide you know for 3% of the log entries,
你可以决定 3% 的日志条目，
you know which ones are going to be appended.
哪个可以被追加。
And so the is a completely different approach,
所以，这是一种完全不同的方法，
that doesn't require solving computational intensive puzzles,
这不需要解决计算密集型难题，
and it seems to get quite a bit of actually attention,
它似乎得到了相当多的关注，
and there are cryptocurrencies that use it,
而且有使用它的加密货币，
and in fact it looks like one of the more major ones Ethereum seems to be slated,
事实上，看起来以太坊是最重要的一个，
where going in the direction of proof-of-stake approach.
正在使用权益证明的方法。
But Bitcoin uses proof-of-work approach,
但是比特币使用的是工作量证明方法，
and so we're just going to proceed with that design.
所以，我们将继续进行这个设计。
Any questions?
有什么问题吗？
So let's, I'm just wondering of
所以，我只是在想，
how it's hard to impersonate the winner,
冒充获胜者有多难，
so let's say that we have server A and server B,
假设我们有服务器 A 和服务器 B ，
and server A wants to append entry, let's say e1,
服务器 A 想要附加条目 e1 ，
and server B wants to append entry e2,
服务器 B 想要附加条目 e2 ，
so server A solves the puzzle and publishes the solution, right,
所以服务器 A 解决了这个难题，并发布了解决方案，
and I'm assuming that the solution is easy to check,
我假设解决方案很容易检查，
so then server B sees the solution and check that it's correct,
然后服务器 B 看到解决方案，并检查其是正确的，
so it cannot work that,
所以它不能工作，
server B just simply re-publishes the solution with its own name,
服务器 B 只是简单地用它自己的名字重新发布解决方案，
and signing it by its own name,
并用自己的名字签名，
because the puzzle for e2 is different from the puzzle for e1, right?
因为 e2 的难题和 e1 的难题是不同的，对吗？
Yeah, okay, yeah exactly,
是的，好的，就是这样，
and we'll see, we'll get into this in more detail in the second,
我们会看到，我们将在稍后看到更多细节。
of course, this here, this is sort of the basic insight,
当然，在这里，这是一种基本的了解，
of course not enough.
当然，这还不够。
But it will turn out to be enough to basically settle on a fork,
但是，这足以决定在哪一个 fork 上，
so we're going to accept,
所以我们要接受，
they're gonna be forks,
它们会 fork ，
and then we're gonna have,
然后我们会有，
Bitcoin basically accepts their forks like SUNDR,
比特币会接受他们的 fork ，像 SUNDR 一样，
then has a way of basically deciding which fork to settle on.
然后有一种决定选择哪一个 fork 的方法。
Yeah, so I had a question about network partitions,
是的，所以我有一个关于网络分区的问题，
and I I was wondering how like,
我想知道如何，
you know if you were able to make a partition like on the Internet,
如果你能在互联网上创建一个分区，
which you know probably unreasonable,
这可能是不合理的，
but you're able to partition the Internet like the whole Internet,
但是你可以划分整个互联网，
and who couldn't you convince,
你不能说服，
like you know one like double spend
某人双重花费，
by like spending on both sides of the partition.
通过在分区的两边花费。
Yeah, the partition never heals?
是的，分区永远不会恢复吗？
Eventually, you'd assume it heals,
最终，如果你认为它会恢复，
but then by then like you probably would have gone in like something shipped.
但到那时，你可能已经发送东西了。
Yeah, so generally we'll see,
是的，所以通常我们会看到，
we'll talk a little bit more about it,
我们会更多地谈论它，
like there's all kind of, there's ways of creating forks,
有各种各样的创建 fork 的方法，
and what you're describing is
你所描述的是
basically for it persists for a long period of time,
因为它会持续很长一段时间，
and you will see that the basically the,
你会看到，
you know Bitcoin basically produces these logs with transactions every ten minutes,
比特币基本上每十分钟产生一次交易日志，
and you know if you're very conservative
如果你非常保守，
or you wanna be careful not to be, avoid double spending
或者你想小心得避免双重花费，
or making sure there's nothing worth double spend,
或者确保没有任何双重花费，
you generally wait you know for multiple these logs to appear, like 5 6,
你通常会等待多个这样的日志显示，比如 5 6 个，
so basically an hour,
所以基本上是一个小时，
before actually decided to actually accept,
在真正决定接受之前，
you know to say yeah, this I'm on the right fork.
说是的，我在正确的 fork 上。
Thanks.
谢谢。
Okay, so.
好的，所以。
Let's also see actually how the pieces fit together,
让我们来看看这些部分如何在一起，
so it turns out you know the,
所以事实证明，
you know do proof-of-work for transaction,
做交易的工作量证明，
it'll be crazy,
它会很疯狂，
because you got to spend a lot of conventional power,
因为你要花费大量的常规的能量，
and for put one single transaction,
为了放入一个单一的事务，
that will limit the number of transactions you can actually do per second,
这将限制你每秒钟执行的交易的数量，
and so the way actually this is done is
所以，完成此操作的一种方式是
basically transaction to a group in blocks
以块为单位对组进行交易处理，
and proof-of-work is going on, on a block basis.
工作量证明以一个块为基础。
So we have our network,
所以我们有自己的网络，
and the way it actually works is that,
它的工作方式是，
we're not making a lot of blocks,
我们不会创建很多块，
but like we made a lot of transactions,
但我们做很多交易，
we make actually a lot of blocks,
我们创建了很多区块，
which are called you know basically blockchain.
也就是区块链。
And so here we got our network,
所以我们有了自己的网络，
you know we have peers around the world,
在世界各地有节点，
and you know the log here is basically a sequence of blocks.
这里的日志是一系列的块。
And so peers have you know copies of these,
所以节点有这些的副本，
you know may create new ones,
可能会创建新的，
append them and distribute them and [] them across the network.
追加它们，分发它们在网络中。
So what is in a, in block, at a very high level,
所以，在非常高的级别上，块中有什么，
again, there are many more details you know that I'm just gonna ignore,
再次，有很多细节我会忽略，
it's gonna be the hash of the previous block,
它是上一个区块的哈希，
so, B-1,
所以 B-1 ，
and so if this is block 5,
如果这是区块 5 ，
you know this is going to be then you know B4, so B-1,
这将是 B4 ，所以 B-1 ，
so the unique identifier of the previous block in the chain,
链中前一个块的唯一标识符，
the transactions that are part of this block,
交易属于这个区块，
and then a nonce, which we'll talk about in a second,
然后是一个 nonce ，我们稍后会谈到，
but this is a thing that is going to play a crucial role in the the puzzle,
但这是一个在难题中发挥关键作用的东西，
and the timestamp,
和时间戳，
and you know this is about typically,
这是典型的，
you'll see a little bit,
你稍后会看到，
you know think about these are roughly a MB you know block,
考虑这些大约是一个 MB 的块，
so basically the the game is
所以这个游戏是
you know the the peers of collect transactions,
收集交易的节点，
then basically solve the puzzle,
然后解决这个难题，
and once they solve the puzzle,
一旦他们解决了难题，
they gonna ship the block to everybody in the in the network,
他们会把这个区块发送给网络中的每个人，
everybody can check whether the peer actually solves the puzzle correctly,
每个人都可以检查节点是否真的正确地解决了难题，
and if you know the puzzle correctly sort of correctly in the transaction checkout,
如果难题在交易检查中正确，
and actually the hash is checkout,
哈希检查，
then they're going to basically accept that block as the next block in the chain.
然后它们会接受这个区块作为链中的下一个区块。
So a little more detail,
所以说得更详细一点，
you know when you know basically the winner gets to the site on the next block,
当获胜者到达下一个区块，
so we have a new block,
所以我们有了一个新的区块，
and this is gonna be the proof-of-work,
这将是工作量证明，
which is done typically the [party] that does the proof-of-work is called the miners,
通常做工作量证明的一方被称为矿工，
we'll see in a second why.
我们很快会知道为什么。
And basically the game that we're going to play is that,
我们要玩的游戏是，
the miner has to compute a hash of this new block,
矿工必须计算这个新数据块的哈希，
for that basically has, has n leading zeros.
为了包含 n 个前导零。
So and the way you know the miner can do that is,
所以，矿工可以做到的方式是，
basically by changing the nonce,
通过改变 nonce ，
so basically the miner makes random guesses for nonce,
所以矿工对 nonce 进行随机猜测，
compute the hash and checks you know the number of leading zeros,
计算哈希并检查前导零的个数，
and if the number of leading zeros you know larger,
如果前导零的数量越大，
then you know basically that block is going to be accepted.
那么这个块是会被接受。
The only way you can think about is,
你可以考虑的唯一办法是，
basically the hash value is below some particular below particular difficulty value,
哈希值低于某个特定难度的值，
this N can be changed over time,
这个 N 可以随着时间的推移而改变，
as we'll see in a second later,
正如我们将在后面看到的，
to you know adjust the difficulty,
来调整难度，
and but on average, you know you know the miner work that is necessary,
但平均而言，矿工工作是必须的，
you know so that they're targeting is about
所以他们的目标是
like a roughly CPU month of computation.
大约一个月的 CPU 计算。
And it's not really expressed in that way,
它并不是以这种方式表达的，
is really expressed in terms of number of hashes you can do per second,
是用每秒可以执行的哈希数来表示的，
but then it boils down to sort of for that kind of number.
但归根结底，这是一种数字。
Of course, a lot of peers you know do this in parallel,
当然，很多节点同时做这个，
you know there I think the network is currently around 10, 000 nodes,
我认为网络目前大约有 10,000 个节点，
10, 000 nodes might be
可能有 10,000 个节点，
and there might be many more miners,
可能会有更多的矿工，
I think hundreds of thousands of miners,
我认为数十万矿工，
and you know they might get lucky
他们可能会幸运，
and you know pick the right nonce very quickly,
很快找到了正确的 nonce ，
and some of them actually get quickly,
他们中的一些人快一点，
and so what they're shooting sort of roughly is that,
所以，他们的目标是，
you know the first one, you know actually solve the puzzle,
第一个解决这个难题，
that it takes about ten minutes.
大约需要十分钟。
I mean you know by adjusting the difficulty
我的意思是，通过调整难度，
or the [] should just you know the time,
或者[]应该只是时间，
where the the time it will take to actually compute one of these hashes energy,
其中计算这些散列能量之一所需的时间，
that one has to put in to actually solve the puzzle.
只有这样才能真正解开这个难题。
And so, whatever you know whatever miner sort of solves this puzzle first,
所以，无论哪个矿工首先解决了这个难题，
basically gets to spread the block across the network,
就在整个网络中传播数据块，
and basically sort of about ten minutes you know to do so, right,
这么做大概需要十分钟，
and so you know, one reason to the ten minutes is there
所以，十分钟的一个原因是，
is going to take a little bit of time to move them one MB of block
移动 1MB 数据块需要一点时间，
across you know many many peers that are in the network,
通过整个网络中的很多节点，
and you want to make sure,
而且，你要确保，
there's enough time to get the the block out to many of the peers,
有足够的时间将区块提供给许多节点，
so that you can avoid forks
这样你就可以避免 fork ，
as we'll see in a second,
我们一会儿就会看到，
so before that somebody else actually you know solves puzzle too.
在其他人也解决了这个难题之前。
Um, professor,
嗯，教授，
so the does a number of leading zeros's
所以需要一些前导零，
that hash needs to be accepted by a node,
哈希值需要被节点接受，
is that number like set by each node individually, like.
它是每个节点单独设置的数字吗？
No, no, it's puzzle of the protocol,
不，不，这是协议的难题，
there's a agreed puzzle.
一个商定的难题。
But, but.
但是，但是。
It's consensus on about N is.
这是关于 N 的共识。
But what I mean is like,
但我的意思是，
it's puzzle of protocol, but like,
这是协议的难题，但是，
so, so, so.
所以，所以，所以。
You can change, will change over time.
你可以改变，也会随着时间的推移而改变。
Well behaved nodes will follow it,
行为良好的节点将跟随它，
but they, but but who calculate, who calculates,
但是谁计算，
that a central server that calculates the N and sends it out everywhere.
一个中央服务器计算出 N 并将它发到所有地方。
No no, we'll see in a second later,
不，不，我们稍后会看到的，
actually how it's computed,
它是如何计算的，
basically I can give you a hint about how it's computed,
我可以给你一个关于它是如何计算的提示，
one reason the timestamps are in these things,
时间戳在里的原因之一，
is that like if the time between a block becomes too low,
如果一个块之间的时间变得太短，
then the difficulty goes up.
然后难度就上升了。
And you know these timestamps of course are validated using the hashes,
当然，这些时间戳是使用哈希值进行验证的，
and all that kind of stuff and sit in the blockchain,
所有这些东西都在区块链中，
everybody sees the same blockchain,
每个人都看到相同的区块链，
so they will compute the same difference between the timestamps,
所以，它们将计算时间戳之间的相同差值，
and therefore make the same adjustment in terms of difficulty.
并在难度方面做出同样的调整。
Right.
好的。
This is one of the cool parts, correct
这是一个很酷的部分，
having a log of everything that's in there,
有一个任何东西的日志，
like if you have some deterministic,
如果你有一些确定性的，
if you could compute any deterministic function over the content of the log.
你可以对日志的内容计算任何确定性函数。
Right, okay,
好的，好的，
so it would be a deterministic function,
所以这将是一个确定性函数，
but at the end of the day,
但归根结底，
like if I like try and get away with like sending less than N like zeros,
比如，如果我尝试发送少于 N 个零，
then each individual node in the network should call me out.
然后网络中的每个节点都会把我赶出来。
Yeah, they will reject your solution,
是的，它们会拒绝你的解决方案，
because you don't have a real solution.
因为你没有真正的解决方案。
Okay, thanks.
好的，谢谢。
So what stops an attacker
那么，是什么阻止攻击者
from just constantly flooding the network with wrong solutions?
不断地向网络发送错误的解决方案？
Yeah, denial service attack
是的，拒绝服务攻击，
and hopefully one of the, turns out that checking the solution is very easy, right,
幸运地是检查解决方案非常容易，
and so it's easy to quickly reject an incorrect solution.
所以，很容易迅速拒绝一个不正确的解决方案。
Thank you.
谢谢。
And how, how are the timestamps determined [],
如何确定时间戳，
like does each block set the timestamp on its own.
比如每个块设置自己的时间戳。
Yeah, the miner that successful mines sets timestamp in the block.
是的，成功开采的矿工在块中设置时间戳。
And what if they just set the timestamp to be like longer than it took,
如果他们将时间戳设置为比所用时间更长的时间，
so that it becomes less difficult.
这样就不那么困难了。
It can't lie too much, correct,
它不能说谎太多，
they have a ten minute window,
他们有 10 分钟的时间，
so roughly to [],
所以粗略地说，
I don't really know exactly how the timestamp is check,
我不知道时间戳是如何检查的，
I don't know, might imagine this solvable.
我不知道，也许可以想象这是可以解决的。
Peers get to the transactions that want to be appended to the block.
获得交易的节点想要附加到块中。
Thank you, that's the next line.
谢谢，这是下一行。
So, so blocks and transactions,
所以，所以块和交易，
so let's assume like there's some
所以让我们假设有一些
you know one B5 that already has been computed,
B5 被计算出来了，
you know that's in the log you know points whatever to B4,
在日志中的，指向 B4 ，
and so we're a miner,
我们是一个矿工，
we're working on
我们工作在，
you know we got a block with,
我们有一个区块，
you know that is sort of reminding on,
这是一种提醒，
so it has a bunch of transactions,
所以它有一些交易，
and we're basically you know trying to compute you know the solution to this puzzle,
我们试着计算这个难题的答案，
and so new transactions coming, right,
所以新的交易来了，
you know they arrived,
它们到了，
and so the new transaction is actually called a memory buffer,
新的交易调用内存缓冲区，
buffer, you're going some buffer,
一个缓冲，你需要一些缓冲，
and basically they're going to when the next block,
它们会到下一个区块，
where going to be at some point,
在某个时刻，
this guy you know let's say this is one miner, miner i,
这个人，假设这是一个矿工 i ，
alright, so let's see miner i is the lucky one,
好的，我们看到矿工 i 是幸运的，
you know actually miner i computes you know the new B6.
矿工 i 计算出新的 B6 。
And so at some point you know B6,
在某个时刻， B6 ，
it's the new next head of the log,
这是日志的新的下一个头部，
you know which contains a bunch of transactions,
包含一堆交易，
and so while you know sort of miner i was actually trying to hash
所以，当矿工 i 试着哈希，
you know computing to many many many hashes to actually solves the puzzle,
计算很多哈希才能解决这个难题，
new transactions come in,
新的交易进来，
so soon as a miner i is done with B6,
在矿工 i 完成 B6 时，
it basically selects you know the number of transactions,
它选择交易数量，
puts a new block together, a partial block,
将一个新的块放在一起，部分块，
it's not the one that is solved yet,
这还不是那个解决的问题，
transactions in from the [pool],
来自[池]的交易，
you know whatever updates, whatever [] needs to be updated,
更新，无论[]需要更新，
and then starts hashing on that one and hoping to solve it,
然后对这个进行哈希并希望解决它，
so that can be added to the transaction log at some point later,
所以，可以在之后的某个时间将其添加到交易日志中。
if it succeeds.
如果它成功了。
Of course, if somebody else succeeds in solving the producing B7 before miner i,
当然，如果其他人在矿工 i 之前成功解决了 B7 ，
you know miner i gonna switch you know to the B7,
矿工 i 将转向 B7 ，
that block remove any transactions that ended up already in B7,
那个块删除已在 B7 中结束所有交易，
and continues with the transactions that are left and are not in B7 yet.
并继续处理剩下的，还不在 B7 中的交易。
Okay, that sort of the plan
好的，这就是方案，
for how exactly the blocks interact at a high level.
关于各个区块如何交互的，在高级别上。
So as as transactions coming in,
所以，随着交易的到来，
like you know trying to calculate the nonce for block,
试着计算区块的 nonce ，
that will like give you know N leading zeros,
这会给你 N 个前导零，
new transactions will come in, right.
新的交易会进来。
As they [], they're not part of that block,
因为它们[]，不是那个区块的一部分，
they're going to be sitting on the side, they're for the next block.
它们将在旁边，它们是下一个区块的。
Okay.
好的。
Could you could you add, could you add them to the.
你能不能把它们加到。
That would change the hash.
那会改变哈希值。
Right, but I mean,
是的，但我的意思是，
you just need to keep trying to get like a nonce, right.
你只需要继续获取一个 nonce 。
But you also have a limit on the block size,
但你也有块大小的限制，
you know block size can't be bigger than one of,
区块大小不能大于，
one some particular predefined constant by the protocol,
协议规定的某个预定义常量，
yeah there's a bunch of other reasons
是的，还有一堆其他原因，
you know once you [] the block you know with your transactions,
一旦[]交易的区块，
you you keep going hashing until you find the solution.
你继续计算哈希，直到你找到解决方案。
Okay.
好的。
Or, or you get.
或者你会得到。
Or you receive a new one and then you reject,
或者你收到一个新的，然后你拒绝，
you go work on the next one.
继续去做下一个。
Okay, thanks.
好的，谢谢。
So when when someone when a miner loses,
所以当矿工输了的时候，
and do they like,
他们是不是，
like is it possible for a miner never to make profit out of this,
比如矿工永远不会从中获利，
because they keep losing,
因为他们一直在输，
because they don't have enough computes.
因为他们没有足够的计算。
Yeah, absolutely,
是的，当然，
if if I would start mining with my laptop,
如果我开始用我的笔记本电脑挖矿，
I'm pretty sure it would make no money.
我很肯定它不会赚到钱。
And the transaction pool, it is local?
交易池，它是本地的吗？
Yeah, every every node maintains a transaction pool,
是的，每个节点都维护着一个交易池，
as they receive transactions from from other nodes in the network,
当它们从网络中的其他节点接收交易时，
you know the the transaction pool
交易池，
and they use that transaction pool basically to fail the next block.
他们使用交易池来使下一个区块失败。
So.
所以。
And all kinds of rules,
以及各种各样的规则，
you know like how you choose select transactions,
比如你如何选择交易，
which I'm not going to talk about.
我不打算谈论这一点。
Okay, so to append, you need to tell your transaction to everyone.
好的，所以要追加，你需要把你的交易告诉每个人。
Yes, or you tell to a bunch of peers
是的，或者你告诉一群节点，
and they will flood it for the rest of you
它们会把它传播给其他节点，
to the rest of the network.
到网络的其余部分。
So for my understanding,
所以，根据我的理解，
when a miner successfully mines or verifies a transaction, they get rewarded.
当一名矿工成功挖掘或核实一笔交易时，他们会得到奖励。
Yeah.
是的。
They did this verification,
他们做了这个核实，
but they can also lie when it comes to the timestamp,
但当涉及到时间戳时，他们也可以撒谎，
so let's say that you have two verifiers
假设你有两个验证者，
and they're both working on the same block,
并且它们都在同一块上工作，
and they almost simultaneously verified at the same time,
而且它们几乎同时核实，
but one of them was you know they lied,
但其中一个，它们撒谎了，
and they made the timestamp a bit earlier,
它们把时间戳做得更早了一点，
so kind of the.
所以有点像。
The difficulties [] for a period of time,
困难[]一段时间，
like for the next like twenty as a whole bunch of years,
比如在接下来的二十年里，
it only changes periodically,
它只会周期性地变化，
you can't change it arbitrarily.
你不能随意改变它。
So was that, I'm sorry, I think I missed that line.
所以是什么，抱歉，我想我错过了这句话。
The difficulty is not changed on every block,
难度并不是在每个区块改变，
it is periodically changed
它会定期更改，
after some number of you know blocks have been computed.
在一定数量的区块计算出来之后。
And so you know it's done in the back,
所以它是在后面完成的，
you know everybody can see what these timestamps are,
每个人都能看到这些时间戳是什么，
you know every, I think every [] with the exact number of blocks were,
我想每个[]有确切数量的区块，
when when you know the difficulties is adjusted.
当难度调整后。
I see.
我明白了。
So at that point you already agreed with all those blocks in the past,
在这一点上，你已经同意了过去所有的区块，
so everybody's in agreed with like what the timestamps are,
所以每个人都达成了一致，时间戳是什么，
that we're going to use to actually compute a new valid block.
我们用来计算一个新的合法的区块。
So, so I I had a question about like achieving consensus,
所以，我有一个关于达成共识的问题，
I guess, like all of this relies on like,
我想所有这一切都依赖于，
pretty much every node running the same code, right,
几乎每个节点都运行相同的代码，
or at least following the rules very, very precisely,
或者至少非常精确地遵守规则，
like what happens, if there's a bug in my code,
如果我的代码中有 bug ，会发生什么，
and the code that I'm running,
我正在运行的代码，
you know maybe a bug in like a bunch of different nodes,
也许有一个 bug 在一堆不同的节点上，
does that [] off like, like all, like notions of like consistency potentially.
这是不是抛出了一致性的概念。
Well, yeah, as long as a majority is,
是的，只要大多数人是，
we'll talk a little bit more about it,
我们会更多地讨论这个问题，
has a majority of the nodes actually that runs the right code,
拥有大多数节点运行正确的代码，
you actually work out.
就能正常工作。
Right, but like if there's a trapdoor in the code,
但如果代码里有后门，
yeah, you've got a problem,
是的，你会遇到麻烦，
like if there's a trapdoor in Linux, you got a problem too.
比如，如果 Linux 中有后门，那么你也会有问题。
So, so do do, does every node run like the same code, or are.
所以，每个节点运行相同的代码，或者是。
There a couple different Bitcoin version around,
有几个不同的比特币版本，
we'll talk a little bit more about in a second,
稍后我们会更详细地讨论，
but there are the main core they're called,
但它们有一个主要的核心，
you know and there like it's like an open source project,
有一个开源项目，
like Linux,
像 Linux 一样，
you know it has maintainers and you know code review and all that kind of stuff.
它有维护者，代码审查和所有类似的事情。
And most of the wallets and most of the peers
而大多数钱包和大多数节点
will run one of the standardized version basically.
都会运行其中一个标准化版本。
Thanks.
谢谢。
Okay, forks.
好了， forks 。
So, wo we know now what the rule is,
所以，我们现在知道规则是什么，
you know who can actually extends a log or the chain [],
谁可以扩展日志或链，
you can still have forks.
你也可以有分叉。
Okay, here's our new [] chain, whatever B5 you know B6,
好的，这是我们新的链， B5 B6 ，
and you know we you know somebody to do may actually gets a lucky,
我们，有人可能真的会很幸运，
and so roughly computes you know B7, two B7 at the same time,
几乎在同一时间计算出 B7 ，
so you're gonna B7',
所以你有 B7' ，
and here we got B7'',
我们这里有 B7'' ，
that would be problematic for us, right,
这对我们来说是有问题的，
because maybe one of these this chain has the transaction
因为这条链中可能有一条交易，
you know the y to whatever y to z,
从 y 到 z ，
yeah, maybe this one has you know y to Q,
也许这个是 y 到 Q ，
when we were on a sort of make sure,
我们在某种程度上确定，
that we actually settle in the end of one chain.
我们会位于一条链上。
So there's two reasons why this change might [],
这一变化可能会[]的原因有两个，
you know one is you know people are participants find the,
一个是参与者找到，
find the nonce at the same time
同时找到了 nonce ，
or roughly at the same time,
或者大致在同一时间，
and the second one is that,
第二个是，
there may be slow networks,
可能存在速度较慢的网络，
and so you know a peer might receive you know from two nodes
一个节点可能会从两个节点接收，
that are different you know network,
从不同的网络上，
at some point, these two new solutions,
在某一点上，有两个新的解决方案，
and basically you know when a node ends up in this situation,
当一个节点在这种情况下结束时，
basically does nothing,
什么都不做，
as usual, keeps the fork around,
像往常一样，继续保留 fork ，
and just waits to see which fork get extended,
等待那个 fork 会扩展，
and so you know maybe this work,
也许这个会工作，
the bottom one will get extended you know B8,
下面这个会扩展， B8 ，
and then the rule is very simple,
然后规则非常简单，
you know the peer switches, switches the longest fork,
节点切换到最长的 fork ，
and, and so, and so basically you know
所以，基本上，
all the transactions you know might have learned about,
所有交易都会知道，
in this fork, in the top fork,
在这个 fork ，上面这个 fork 中，
just going to disappear,
就这么消失了，
you know there's gonna not matter in the system,
这个在系统里不会有什么问题，
because in the end,
因为最终，
you know all those good nodes will actually agree on the longest chain
所有这些好的节点都会在最长的链上达成一致，
and basically proceed mining along the longest chain.
沿着最长的链进行采矿。
That's the basic plan,
这是基本的方案，
and so, let's look a little bit about
所以，让我们来看看，
how would that solve our double double spending problem.
这将如何解决我们的双重花费问题。
Wait, I have a question on your slide.
稍等，我对你的幻灯片有个问题。
Yep, I'm gonna continue previous slide in this slide.
是的，我将在这张幻灯片继续上一张幻灯片。
Oh, okay, so.
哦，好的，那么。
If you have any question, so.
如果你有任何问题，那么。
So even if the in the, in the second cause, like the slow network,
所以，即使在第二个原因中，比如网络速度慢，
can't you detect that,
你能不能检测到，
if you if the miner included the timestamp
如果矿工包含的时间戳，
where they found when they found the solution?
当他们找到解决方案时？
Yeah, okay, the.
是的，好的。
You might already be suspicious or may agree on
你可能已经心存疑虑或者可能同意，
what actually the next what the right probably the right chain is,
什么是下一个正确的链，
but it will be confirmed later by future blocks,
但这将在之后的区块得到确认，
and you use the future blocks do really decide what longest chain is.
而你使用的未来的区块确实最长的链是什么。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, double spending,
好的，双重花费，
so let's talk about two easy two cases,
那么让我们来谈谈两个案例，
when the first one is easy,
第一个很容易，
you know y sends, you know the y to z and y to Q,
y 发送 ， y 到 z ， y 到 Q ，
to some peer or to the peers,
给某个节点，
and basically what will happen in this case is that,
在这种情况下会发生的是，
it's a well behaving peer,
它是一个正常的节点，
you'll see like hey you know
你会看到，实际上我花了两次相同的钱的交易将被拒绝，
two transactions that actually spent the same money twice are going to reject,
花费相同钱两次的交易会被拒绝，
that a peer that receives was trying to
收到的节点试着，
or a miner that is going to construct a block,
或者一个矿工组件区块，
and it actually validate all the transactions,
它验证所有交易，
before they stick them in the block.
在把它们放入区块之前。
So this whole you know don't really this is not gonna work,
所以这不会奏效，
miners gonna reject, good miners.
好的矿工会拒绝。
Okay, the second question, the more interesting,
好的，第二个问题，更有趣，
I think cases basically y sends, y to z, to some set of peers,
y 发送， y 到 z ，给一些节点，
and then y to Q, to another set of peers.
然后 y 到 Q ，到另一组节点。
And you know we, and then might you know,
然后可能，
maybe you know the maybe one pool was bigger than the other pool,
也许一个池比另一个大，
but it could actually end up in a situation,
但它可能会是一种情况，
where basically we got the chain as before,
像之前一样，我们得到了链，
and basically either once it appears you know computes you know the hash,
一旦它出现计算哈希值，
where that includes y to Q,
其中包括 y 到 Q ，
and the other one computes a block you know actually contains y to z.
另一个计算包含 y 到 z 的块。
So this looks like a double spending thing,
所以这看起来像是双重花费的事情，
and so if you're z, correct,
所以如果你是 z ，
z is the person that is going to decide
z 是做决定的人，
whether to accept you know this transaction
是否接受这笔交易，
and hand out, the hand out the latte,
并发出拿铁，
what you do is you're gonna wait,
你要做的就是等待，
and you're gonna wait until
你要等到直到
there's a bunch of more blocks that are behind it,
有很多块在它后面，
so typically it's 5 6, up to 5 6,
所以通常是 5 6 ，
you know for a very valuable transaction,
对于一个非常有价值的交易，
maybe not for a latte,
可能不是一杯拿铁，
but if you're buying a car,
但如果你要买车，
you really want to make damn sure,
你真的想要确定，
that you're gonna get your money,
你会拿到你的钱，
and that you know y didn't double spend the money,
而且 y 没有双重花费他的钱，
so, you may where wait for a while
所以，你可能等待一段时间，
until new hash has been ended,
直到新的哈希结束，
to a new blocks being extended to the blockchain,
到一个新的区块扩展到区块链，
and you know once you have 5 or 6,
一旦你有 5 6 个，
you know the paper does some calculations,
论文做了一些计算，
you're going to be pretty confident, you're very confident that,
你会非常自信，
that it's unlikely you know for attacker to basically compute a new chain
攻击者计算出一条新链，
and sort of overtake you know the longer chain, right,
并且超过更长的链，
let's say this is the attacker,
假设这是攻击者，
the attacker has less computational power,
攻击者的计算能力较弱，
they are presumably on the assumption behind this whole paper
他们在论文的假设中，
has less computational power than all the good people,
弱于所有好人的计算能力，
and so if the good people have more computational power,
所以，如果好人有更多的计算能力，
it's going to be impossible for the attacker
对于攻击者来说，这是不可能的，
unlikely or the [] will be impossible
不太可能，或者不可能
or unlikely for the attacker to compute faster,
或不太可能让攻击者计算得更快，
and actually make a chain that is longer than the good chain.
做出一个比好链更长的链。
So that's sort of the key assumption that's behind all this,
所以，这是这一切背后的关键假设，
among this reason reason.
这其中原因。
And so basically z you know just has to wait for a while
所以 z 只需要等待一段时间，
until the good guys are extended to chain long enough,
在好人延长到足够长的链条之前，
that you know z is completely convinced that,
z 完全相信，
you know it's impossible for a set of attackers,
攻击者是不可能的，
to actually out compute you know the good people.
算力超过好人。
And at that point you know z can just accept the transaction,
在这一点上， z 可以接受交易，
and say like oh this is legit transaction,
然后说，这是合法的交易，
if everything else checks out,
如果其他一切都没问题，
and handover the latte or a car you know to z, to y I guess.
然后把拿铁或者车交给 z ，或交给 y 。
Sorry, quick question, who distributes the puzzles?
抱歉，一个小问题，谁分发这些难题的？
There's no distribution puzzles necessary, right,
没有必要分配难题，
the puzzle is you know predetermined,
难题是预先确定的，
you know the puzzle is
这个难题是，
you have to compute a hash over the block that has enough leading zeros,
你必须通过块计算出一个哈希值，有足够的前导零，
so theres no distribution of the puzzle,
所以没有难题的分发，
the only thing that's distributed maybe its difficulty,
唯一被分发的东西可能是它的难度，
but as we talk a little bit earlier,
但正如我们之前所说的，
that sort of adjusted over time in a deterministic way.
这种情况通过时间以一种确定性的方式进行调整。
Thank you.
谢谢。
So there's all these transactions that are happening
所以所有这些发生的交易，
and then through some gossip protocol or something,
然后通过一些 gossip 协议或者别的什么，
the transaction distributed to all the nodes,
交易被分发给所有节点，
and then somehow there's agreement on
然后达成一致，
what set of transactions are packaged into a block,
哪些交易打包成一个块，
so everyone has agreement on what the block is.
每个人都对区块达成了一致。
No no no no no, no, the miner receives transactions, right,
不，不出，矿工收到交易，
we go here, where was it,
我们到这里，它在哪里，
block, there was some slide.
区块，有一些幻灯片。
I think the next one.
我想是下一个。
Yeah, blocks in transactions,
是的，交易中的块，
so the miner, maybe miner I you know just receive transactions over the network,
所以矿工，可能是矿工 i 通过网络接收交易，
and it just decides which transactions go in that block,
它决定将哪些交易放在该块中，
and it starts computing,
然后它开始计算，
and if it wins,
如果它赢了，
that is the transactions that go in that block.
这就是进入那个区块的交易。
I see.
我明白了。
So that determines the total order,
所以这决定了总的顺序，
you know the total order is disturbed by all the previous blocks,
总顺序是由之前的块分发的，
can approach this new block and within a block,
可以接近这个新的块，
basically miner I is deciding what goes in,
矿工 i 决定什么东西进去，
and there's some complicated rules,
而且还有一些复杂的规则，
that miners are supposed to follow,
矿工们应该遵循的，
but basically the miner gets to decide.
但是，矿工可以做出决定。
Thank you.
谢谢。
And there are certain incentive systems for the miners to do the right thing.
而且有一定的激励制度让矿工们做正确的事情。
So let me talk a little bit about this,
所以让我谈一下这个问题，
so so far, you know we've seen the this puzzle,
到目前为止，我们看到了这个难题，
that's sort of the core of this proof-of-work idea,
这是工作量证明想法的核心，
is actually the core of actually achieving consensus,
是真正达成共识的核心，
and, but you know this requires the miners actually do quite a bit of work,
但是这需要矿工们做相当多的工作，
you know like they have to hash hash hash, have a serious computer,
他们必须计算哈希，拥有一台好的计算机，
one, one we saw roughly a month work,
我们看到大约一个月的工作，
and so why would a miner do that,
那么为什么一个矿工要这么做，
and so there's an incentive system
所以，有一个激励系统
for to encourage miners to actually play this role.
来鼓励矿工扮演这个角色。
And you know there's a rule,
这里有一条规则，
that basically there a bunch of Bitcoins reserved in the pool,
有一些比特币保留在池中，
like when first bits you know Bitcoin transactions are created,
比如第一批比特币交易被创建时，
and miners get paid were rewarded out of the pool,
矿工们从池子里拿到了奖励，
and so this was the first transaction,
所以这是第一笔交易，
transaction in the block is basically a reward for the miner.
区块中的交易是对矿工的奖励。
And so basically the miner can insert transaction
所以矿工可以插入交易
in the first [] transaction, the first slot,
在第一个[]交易中的块，第一个插槽，
where that basically is the miner's public key
这是矿工的公钥，
and transferring money out of the pool to himself or herself.
把钱从池中转到他自己身上。
And and that is the way that miner can actually,
这就是矿工可以，
get namely sort of return or reward for actually the work they do,
他们所做的工作得到某种回报或奖励，
that reward changes over time,
这种奖励会随着时间的推移而变化，
currently I think you know were
现在我想是，
you know today is I think it's 6.25 Bitcoin
今天我想是 6.25 比特币，
to actually mined a block,
才能真正开采一个区块，
but this changes over time,
但随着时间的推移，这种情况会发生变化，
it actually has a halving rule,
它有一个减半规则，
that reduces you know a half,
减少一半，
a couple years ago, a twelve bit 12.5 Bitcoin,
几年前，是 12.5 比特币，
in a couple in a while will be
在一段时间之后，
whatever three points, you know whatever the half of 6.25
三点几， 6.25 的一半，
and I think I remember correctly every two and every 210,000 blocks,
我记得每 21 万个区块，
that number halves,
这个数字减半，
it's until it runs into the most finest finest Bitcoin denominator,
直到它遇到了最可接受的比特币分母，
and then basically stops.
然后就会停下来。
But we're a while away,
但我们还有一段时间，
before that actually is the case,
在这种情况之前，
if that happens,
如果发生这种情况，
then, the idea is that
然后，想法是，
to mine actually block every transaction pays a little fee,
为了挖一个区块，每一个交易都需要支付一点费用，
and the miner collects the fees you know from all the transactions in the block,
矿工收取区块所有交易的费用，
and use and rewards the miner with those fees,
并用这些费用奖励矿工，
even now there are some fees,
即使是现在也有一些费用，
but to make sure that basically,
但要确保做到这一点，
the transactions are not [],
这些交易并不是[]，
and so really the miner actually earns not only 6.25,
所以实际上矿工的收入不仅是 6.25 ，
but also like the fees actually,
但是费用，
and the fees that actually go along with the transactions.
还有伴随交易而来的费用。
Okay, that's the minor incentive.
好的，这是次要的激励。
In you know Bitcoin has gotten so successful,
比特币已经变得如此成功，
that basically there's sort of an arms race in miners,
是一种矿工的军备竞赛，
and this is like for example,
这就像是，
why you know if I would want to participate,
如果我想参与，
and actually when they make some money,
当他们赚到一些钱，
I'm going to lose,
我就要输钱，
because the serious miners are much better at computing a hash,
因为好的矿工更擅长计算哈希，
is at a very high rate,
效率非常高，
than you know your standard laptop can.
比你的标准笔记本能做到的。
And so there's a couple of things actually go on in this arms race,
所以，在这场军备竞赛中，发生了几件事，
first of all, the miners for pools,
首先是，矿工池，
so the basic idea is that,
所以基本的想法是，
the miners collaborate with each other
矿工们彼此合作，
and share the revenue with each other,
并相互分享收入，
and so you know if your pool with many many, many nodes,
所以如果你的池有很多很多节点，
you know maybe you know from different people,
也许来自不同的人们，
many computers from different people,
来自不同人的许多电脑，
the people could share the revenue stream out of mining,
人们可以分享采矿带来的收入流，
and because they do this as a pool,
因为它们是作为一个池来做的，
you know they're more likely to actually win and once in a while
他们更有可能赢，
and you know of course probabilistically, they have some chance to win,
当然从概率上讲，他们有一些获胜的机会，
and basically you know spreads of the income stream
通过收入流传播
in a more stable form across all the miners in a single pool.
以更稳定的形式在单一池中的所有矿工之间分配。
So if you [] you look online today,
所以，如果你今天在网上看的话，
there are some really large pools,
有一些非常大的池，
and nothing like the three biggest pools
而且没有什么比得上三大池，
contribute to contribute more than 50% of the mining power.
贡献出 50% 以上的采矿算力。
I'm sorry, why,
抱歉，为什么，
is this, why you said that each block takes around ten minutes to mine,
这就是你说的为什么每个块都需要大约 10 分钟的时间来挖掘，
even though it takes a month of CPU power.
尽管它需要一个月的 CPU 能力。
Yeah, on averages a month,
是的，平均一个月，
but you know you're gonna have some lucky,
但你会有一些幸运的，
you, you pick the nonce,
你选择了 nonce ，
you know get lucky and actually picking nonce,
很幸运，选择了 nonce ，
that actually allows you to solve the problem much quicker, right,
可以让你更快地解决问题，
there's always a probability,
总是有一个概率，
nonce on some big number
nonce 是某些大数，
and if you pick the right number,
如果你选对了数字，
you know you can get lucky
你可以很幸运，
and have many many, many miners do that,
有很多矿工这样做，
there's actually a chance,
是有可能的，
you don't take much less than a month,
你只需要不到一个月的时间，
and in fact, that's why where ten minutes comes from.
这就是十分钟的由来。
Wait, oh, is is the month more important or ten minutes more important,
等等，是一个月更重要还是十分钟更重要，
because if there was only one miner, right,
因为如果只有一个矿工，
on the expected is one month, you,
预计是一个月，
on average it would take one month, right?
平均下来要一个月，对吧？
Yeah, but there going to do something is there are many many miners.
是的，但是有很多很多矿工。
But what what it like very,
但如果有，
like if there's a lot more miner,
如果有很多矿工，
miner it's clear the ability of.
矿工的能力是显而易见的。
There's a lot of variation, but on average ten minutes,
有很多变量，但平均是 10 分钟，
[] that is on average comes out to be ten minutes.
[]的平均时间是十分钟。
Okay.
好的。
Is it ever possible that like a puzzle is impossible?
有没有可能，难题是不可能的？
No, I don't think so, it may take a long time.
不，我不这么认为，可能要花很长时间。
There's gonna be,
将会有，
well, there's gonna be you get to pick the nonce, correct,
好的，你可以选择 nonce ，
and you know there's going to be a case
会有这种情况，
where the hash is going to fall within N leading zeros.
哈希将落在 N 个前导零之内。
And so like how,
所以如何，
so since the value of Bitcoin is actually very, let's say volatile,
由于比特币的价值实际上非常不稳定，
and so then how can we actually ensure that
那么我们如何才能确保
the incentive system for miners is still adequate
矿工的激励制度仍然足以
to keep this thing going for the future,
让这件事在未来继续下去，
I mean since the number of like since the reward is predetermined,
我的意思是因为奖励数量是预先确定的，
let's say to be 6.25 Bitcoins,
假设是 6.25 比特币，
what if for some reason the Bitcoin value has dropped,
如果由于某种原因，比特币的价值下跌了，
and then the incentive is not good enough for the miners,
然后，对矿工来说，激励措施不够好，
and so I just think.
所以我只是觉得。
Yeah you know there's actually no value for miners to do this,
是的，矿工们这样做没有任何价值，
then you know the Bitcoin network collapse,
然后比特币网络崩溃了，
and presumably the way this is gonna work out
假设这件事会解决的，
is the transaction fees go up.
就是交易费用上涨。
But then if the transaction fees go up,
但如果交易费用上涨，
then it will, it will be a counter incentive for people who could use it.
那么，对于可能使用它的人来说，这将是一种相反的激励。
Yeah yeah, but like if everybody's on the Bitcoin network,
是的，但是如果每个人都在比特币网络上，
if you want to trade goods,
如果你想交易商品，
you know you have to deal with somebody on the Bitcoin network,
你必须与比特币网络上的某个人交易，
so there's all kinds of complicated analysis,
所以有各种各样的复杂分析，
that I'm not gonna like predict on like what's gonna be the outcome.
我不想预测结果会是什么。
I see, okay.
我明白了，好的。
Well, I guess we seen two 2140,
我想在 2140 年，
and that's sort of the point where I think the reward system runs out,
这是奖励制度用尽的时候，
it's gonna be all based on transaction fees, and with the current rate.
将完全基于交易费用，按照目前的速率。
I see, thanks.
我明白了，谢谢。
Okay, so the other thing that's going on is
好的，另一件事是，
you know people build special hardware,
人们建造特殊的硬件，
there are companies that you know delivery boards,
有一些公司发布板，
you know that are really good at fast at hashing,
它们很擅长快速计算哈希，
and these are used by the miner pools,
这些是矿工池使用的，
people try they have high speed links to many peers,
他们有到许多节点的高速链路，
so if they find a block,
所以如果他们找到了一个区块，
they can actually get it out first
他们可以先把它拿出来，
and so they win, etc etc.
所以他们赢了，等等。
So this is you know if you're interested in this,
如果你对这个感兴趣的话，
you can read lots and lots of information about it online,
你可以在网上读到很多关于它的信息，
you know still the system seems to be hanging together.
这些系统仍然是在一起的。
Okay, let me talk a little bit about a whole bunch of practical issues,
好的，让我来谈谈一大堆实际问题，
that I sort of ignored,
我有点忽略了，
although we touched on it a bit.
尽管我们略有触及。
So, so first, ten minutes,
所以，首先是十分钟，
I think ten minutes is basically [] time you know the sort of upper bound,
我认为 10 分钟是[]时间的上限，
where like you know, like ten times the time roughly to flood the network.
大概十次传播到网络的时间。
So Bitcoin try to avoid you know these are a sort of privilege,
所以比特币试图避免一种特权，
you know privilege fork,
特权分叉，
where basically you know two nodes at the same time roughly compute,
两个节点几乎同时计算，
and therefore extends the chain roughly at the same time,
大致同时扩展一条链，
and want to try to avoid that,
想要尽量避免这样，
and so one way to avoid that is,
所以，避免这种情况的一种方法是，
to basically give enough time to the nodes
为了给节点留出足够的时间，
to sort of get the, the block out you know to a many many many peers,
让区块到达很多节点，
so that most peers actually know about it,
让大多数节点都知道它，
and then you know so that's where the ten minutes comes from.
这就是十分钟的由来。
Of course, the block size determines the [] transaction per second,
当然，区块大小决定了每秒的交易，
the block size is roughly megabyte,
区块大约是兆字节，
and so you know you're gonna do one block per you know roughly 10 minutes,
所以，大约每隔 10 分钟做一个区块，
then you know the number of transactions is is limited to
然后交易的数量被限制为，
the number of, the number of transaction that fit in a single block,
能够容纳在单个数据块中交易数量，
and that is a number of transactions, you can do.
这是你可以做到的交易数量。
And it turns out that, for today, you know that the number of transactions is,
在今天，交易的数量是，
like you get in the thousands per second to work out the numbers,
每秒几千次的速度计算出数字，
and that's sufficient,
这就足够了，
for example there's probably an analogy,
例如，有一个类比，
people which made it bigger than the Visa network,
人们使它比 Visa 网络更大，
more transaction of Visa can process,
Visa 可以处理更多的交易，
by presumably is not big enough to actually,
可能还不够大，
basically run all transactions you know money transaction the world across.
运行世界各地的所有货币交易。
Another big, I will come back to this in a second,
另一个大的，我稍后会回到这个问题上来，
another big issue is that,
另一个大问题是，
changes to the protocol, change require consensus,
改变协议，改变需要达成共识，
and in some cases this is easy, right,
在某些情况下，这很容易，
some changes are easy,
有些改变是很容易的，
there's one easy changes,
有一个简单的变化，
for example the number of leading zeros,
例如前导零的数量，
you know there's basically deterministic algorithm
有一种确定性的算法
to compute from the past log entries,
根据过去的日志条目进行计算，
what the difficulty is going to be for future puzzles.
对于未来的难题来说，难度是什么。
And since this would be deterministic of function of the log,
由于这将是日志的函数的确定性，
there's nothing that changes,
没有什么能改变，
basically an easy,
一个简单的，
there's a bunch of other parameters in the protocol,
在协议中还有一堆其他参数，
but that kind of flavor.
但是另一种风格。
Some changes however result in a soft work,
一些变化导致了软工作，
we talked a little bit about,
我们稍微谈了一下，
let's say, you know the main software, main distribution,
比如，主要软件，主要发布，
the core distribution for Bitcoin I want to make a change,
比特币的核心发布做出改变，
there are the sort of incompatible,
有一些不相容的，
then you're gonna have old clients
然后，你会有旧客户端
or clients running with the old software,
或使用旧软件运行的客户端，
peers running with the old software and new peers new software,
运行旧软件的节点和新软件的新节点，
and that will temporarily you know may create some forks,
这会暂时产生一些分叉，
of course you know the some communication going on,
当然，有一些通信正在进行，
and in the long run,
从长远来看，
you know probably people will settle on the new fork with the new software.
人们很可能会选择安装了新软件的新分叉。
Some changes actually result in a hard fork,
有些变化导致硬分叉，
so, for example, there was a couple years ago,
例如，几年前，
there was a lot of discussion about this block size,
有很多关于这个块大小的讨论，
some people in the community,
社区里的一些人，
community want to increase the block size,
社区想要增加区块大小，
so other people don't want to increase the block size,
其他人不想增加块大小，
and basically you know they split,
然后他们分裂了，
and there's corresponds with two Bitcoin or two Bitcoin forks running,
对应于两个比特币分叉，
in fact, there's probably more than two,
事实上，可能不止两个，
but like that one resolved in [] and hard forks split.
但那次解决的硬分叉。
So, sort of an interesting you know aspect
所以，有一个有趣的方面，
consensus into kind of systems,
共识进入这些系统，
that you're going to have these kinds of practical problems,
你会遇到这样的实际问题，
that actually can really into soft fork or in hard fork,
它可以导致软分叉或硬分叉，
because people just don't want to collaborate on a particular form.
因为人们不想在特定的形式上进行合作。
Any questions about this?
对此有什么问题吗？
What happens in hard forks?
在硬分叉上，发生了什么？
You have two two different blockchains,
你有两个不同的区块链，
and clients have to choose which fork they want to be.
客户端必须选择他们想要跟随哪个分叉。
Interesting.
有意思。
Or publish their transactions in both, I don't know.
或者在这两个都发布他们的交易，我不知道。
I mean, but you have like, I mean say I have a couple Bitcoin,
我的意思是，假如我有几个比特币，
I'll have a couple of Bitcoin both forks, right,
我会在两个分叉都有几个比特币，
but I can start spending them,
我可以开始花费它们，
and either, like.
或者，比如。
Well, you have you have Bitcoins in the prefix of those, correct,
好的，你有那些前缀的比特币，
so and both forks have the prefix,
所以两个分叉都有前缀，
so you can't, you can't double spend your money.
所以你不能重复花钱。
Ha?
什么？
Well, so actually in in the case of,
那么，在这种情况下，
like when Bitcoin fork there was a hard fork
当比特币有一个硬分叉，
and in the one of the new forks was called Bitcoin cash,
其中一个新的分叉被称为比特币现金，
all the tokens were duplicated within the value of the tokens,
所有代币都是在代币的价值内复制的，
it wasn't like you doubled your values,
你没有双倍你的价值，
like the price of Bitcoin decrease
比特币所减少的价值，
and then the difference in that decrease was the value of the Bitcoin cash,
然后减少的差额是比特币现金的价值，
so, is think of it like a stock split,
所以，可以把它想象成股票拆分，
like you get more tokens,
你得到了更多的代币，
but the actual value would stay the same,
但实际价值保持不变，
because you know increasing the supply of tokens.
因为增加了代币的供应。
Okay, great.
好的，很好。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Okay good, let me summarize now.
好的，现在让我来总结一下。
So, basically what we see here is gonna distribute consensus,
所以，我们在这里看到的是分步共识，
with an open distributed systems with potentially Byzantine participants,
具有潜在拜占庭参与者的开放分布式系统，
which let me see, if my program crashed, hold on a second.
让我看看，我的程序是否崩溃了，稍等一下。
So this consensus is with Byzantine potentially Byzantine participants.
所以，这种共识是潜在的拜占庭参与者的共识。
And you know the you know the the thing that actually is being reached consensus
事情达到共识，
on this public ledger or public log, if you will,
在这个公开账本或公开日志上，
the basic orders, all the transactions ever since the beginning of time
从时间开始以来的所有交易，
and allow people to check what the balances are of every public key,
并允许人们检查每个公钥的余额是多少，
and avoid double spending,
并避免重复花费，
and you know the particular cool sort of the idea here is
这里特别酷的想法是，
to basically just proof-of-work idea
工作量证明的想法，
to determine actually who is allowed to extend the block chain.
确定允许谁扩展区块链。
Okay?
好的？
So it's basically all I want to say,
所以这就是我想说的，
so if you need to run and leave,
所以如果你需要离开，
feel free to leave
请随意离开，
and this is basically the end of this lecture,
这节课到此结束，
anybody wants to stay and ask more questions,
任何人想留下来问更多问题，
please feel free to stay,
请留下来，
on Thursday, there's no lecture, it's a hacking day,
星期四没有课，它是黑客日，
as you know, that Friday is the deadline
如你所知，周五是最后期限，
for the final project or lab 4 whatever you'll be doing,
对于最后的项目或你选择的实验 4 。
so, good luck, trying to get that work finished.
所以，祝你好运，努力完成这个工作。
And we'll talk in the next class, meeting next Tuesday.
我们将在下周二讨论下一节课。
Okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Oh, could you talk a little bit more about the proof-of-stake?
哦，你能不能再多谈一点关于权益证明？
Sure, I'm not sure what to say about it,
当然，我不知道该怎么说，
the you know if you want to know any more details,
如果你想知道更多细节，
you know just Google proof-of-stake,
只需要谷歌 proof-of-stake ，
and you'll find a different Bitcoin currencies that use it,
你会发现一种不同的比特币货币使用它，
and and that will tell you more detail,
会告诉你更多细节，
but basically you know the power of in the network
但基本上网络中的权力，
is proportional to proof-of-stake in the network,
与网络中的权益证明成正比，
and the basic idea is that,
基本的想法是，
if you own like whatever 3% or 10% of all the Bitcoins,
如果你拥有所有比特币的 3% 或 10% ，
you know you guys to decide 10% of the the new blocks,
你能决定 10% 的新区块，
and you're going to have incentive, you know the higher your stake,
你会得到激励，更多的权益，
you know the higher incentives actually to play the game correctly.
更高的激励来玩这个游戏。
So the struggle becomes more deterministic in that case, right?
所以，在这种情况下，斗争变得更具确定性，对吗？
All depends on the details of the protocol,
所有都取决于协议的细节，
in algorithm, you know basically there's a periodical leader,
在算法方面，有一个周期性的领导者，
and there's a committee election,
还有一个委员会选举，
and then the committee decides someone like what the next block is,
然后委员会决定下一个区块是什么，
and then you know there's a new leader
然后有一个新的领导者，
and the new committee elections etc etc.
以及新的委员会选举，等等。
And many aspects of that, are you know probably stick and randomized,
其中的许多方面，可能是固定的和随机的，
so that the attacker can win the game.
所以攻击者可能赢得游戏。
These protocol are quite sophisticated.
这些协议是相当复杂的。
Also to be able to mine
另外，为了能够挖掘，
you have to have of the log to verify the transactions, right?
你必须拥有日志来验证交易，对吧？
Yes.
是的。
Yeah, so the miners is a complete copy of the log which is gigabyte.
是的，矿工复制了整个日志， GB 级别。
Isn't that a lot?
是不是太多了？
It turned out to be totally doable for a reasonable computer.
对于一台合理的计算机来说，这是完全可行的。
Okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
You're welcome.
不用谢。
This is unrelated to the lecture,
这与课程无关，
but do you think it'd be possible
但是你认为是否有可能
to talk about during the classroom time
在课堂上谈论，
like the design that TAs that you had for lab 3 and 4,
比如助教对实验 3 和 4 的设计，
like because there's more open-ended, so.
因为有更多的开放式，所以。
Yeah, certainly more open-ended.
是的，当然更多的是开放式的。
I was not planning to,
我没打算这么做，
I don't know we have time left to do so,
我不知道我们还有时间这么做，
first of all, not everybody has done lab 4,
首先，并不是每个人都做过实验 4 ，
and so I currently have no intention to do so,
所以我目前没有这样做的打算，
but of course you can reach out to our office hours
当然，你可以到我们的办公时间，
and talk to the TA soon,
和助教谈谈，
or again reach out later to me
或者稍后再联系我，
and we can talk about lab 3 and lab 4.
我们可以讨论实验 3 和实验 4 。
Sounds good, thank you.
听起来不错，谢谢。
So, so I I had a question about,
所以，我有个问题，
like it says, it says in the paper like, or rather, sorry,
就像论文中说的，或者，抱歉，
yeah, once the latest transaction in a coin is buried under enough blocks,
一旦硬币中最新的交易放在足够的区块中，
the spent transaction before it can be discarded to save disk space.
它之前花费的交易可以放弃来节省磁盘空间。
I I I I understood though that you know a blockchain,
我知道区块链，
never really like discards transactions,
从来不会丢弃交易，
it keeps a whole log of all the transactions,
它保存着所有交易的完整日志，
why is this, like why was this done in practice.
为什么要在实践中这样做。
Because to save space on the, save space on the,
因为为了节省空间，
allow it's a space compaction on the nodes in the miners.
允许矿工节点上的空间压缩。
And so they don't have to keep track of every transaction in the log,
所以，他们不必跟踪日志中的每一笔交易，
over every basically Bitcoin,
每一个比特币，
they have to keep track of the last one and efficient,
他们必须跟踪最后一个，并且足够，
and so one way to think about is
所以，一种考虑的方法是，
sort of like you can compute a snapshot in time of all the values of all the points,
你可以按时间计算出所有点所有值的快照，
and then you don't really have to remember the whole past.
然后你就不需要记住所有过去了。
Who does keep the whole past then?
那么谁会保留整个过去呢？
Yeah, there's two things,
是的，有两件事，
one is like you know when you check whether transaction's valid,
一个是，当你检查交易是否有效时，
go scan the whole log,
去扫描整个日志，
people don't do that you know take forever,
人们不会这么做，
and basically build a data structure is no quite impact,
而构建一个数据结构没有太大的影响，
and has the last transaction for every unspent coin,
有每一个没有花掉的硬币的最后一笔交易，
the you know you can totally download the whole log,
你完全可以下载整个日志，
you know from you want from the Internet,
从互联网上，
it is maintained and nodes to store it,
它被维护，并由节点保存，
you know to basically they lose all the data,
他们会丢失所有的数据，
they can compute all the balances
他们可以计算出所有的余额，
basically from running all the transaction from beginning of time.
从一开始就运行所有的交易。
But so so like, if people are like who maintains the whole block,
但是，如果人们，谁维护整个区块，
the whole transactions.
整个交易。
Replicated everywhere, right,
复制到任何地方，
everybody wants to get a copy of the log.
每个想得到日志的人。
Right.
是的。
But, but if most people are doing this it's cutting transactions,
但是，如果大多数人都截断交易，
like why would someone keep like the.
为什么有人会一直保持。
This is not good enough to actually keep track of,
这还不够好，真正跟踪，
you know this allows you to decide
这让你可以决定
where the transaction was actually happened in the past,
交易在过去发生在哪里，
but it doesn't allow you to validate transactions,
但它不允许你验证交易，
so you want to validate transactions you have to keep the past.
所以，你想要验证，就必须保留过去的交易。
Okay, okay, thanks.
好的，好的，谢谢。
You're welcome.
不用谢。
Any more questions?
还有什么问题吗？
Okay, thanks.
好的，谢谢。